Guide to the Isaac Jones Young Films RL.11795
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Isaac Jones Young Films
1933-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Young, Isaac Jones, 1914-1962
Ōfuji, Noburō, 1900-1961
RL.11795
14 items 8mm film reels
1.5 Linear Feet
122 Gigabytes MKV (FFV1) digital preservation files
Fourteen 8mm motion picture films created or collected by Isaac Jones Young, III, of Henderson, North Carolina, primarily documenting his time spent in China in the late 1930s.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
Isaac Jones Young, III, was born in Henderson, North Carolina, in 1914, the son of Celestia Gill Young and Isaac Jones Young, II, the postmaster of Henderson and a community leader who was elected to the North Carolina state legislature for two terms. Jones graduated from Henderson High School in 1931. By the late 1930s he was in China, working for British-American tobacco firm Yi Tsoong, which produced over half the cigarettes made in China at that time. In 1947, Jones married Mary Harrison Bennett (born 1923), also of Henderson, NC, in Shanghai. Mary Bennett Young died in Mexico City in 1957, and Jones remarried in 1958, to Vesta Manning Wester (born 1925), of Henderson, NC. Young died at Duke Hospital, of a pancreatic ailment, in 1962.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Digitized use copies of the films are available for viewing.
Provenance
The Isaac Jones Young films were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Collection Overview
The Isaac Jones Young Films contains fourteen 8mm films made primarily by Isaac Jones Young, III, of Henderson, North Carolina. Eleven of the films document Jones's experiences in China, particularly around Shanghai and Tianjin, during the period 1936 to 1940, when he was employed by the Yi Tsoong Tobacco Company (British-American Tobacco's British Cigarette Company). Images include Shanghai in the aftermath of the Japanese invasion of China as part of the Sino-Japanese War, temples and parks in Beijing, a tobacco market and factory, the 1939 Tianjin Flood, stilt walkers, and Young's European/American colleagues in China. One of the films captures a birthday party at Young's family home in Henderson, NC. Two of the films were collected by Young, including a Kodak Cinefilm promotional reel profiling Hawaii, and a silent, black and white print of anime pioneer Noburo Ofuji's 1933 film, The Three Fearless Frogs (Kaeru sanyushi).
Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945; Tobacco industry -- China; Audiovisual materials; 8mm (photographic film size); Animated films -- Japan; Americans -- China; Temples -- China
- Films, 1933-1940
  Scope and Contents
  Creation dates of the films are estimates based on the edge codes of the film stock as well as the date stamps, where they appear, on the mailers Young used to send the films to Kodak for development.
  - 蛙三勇士, Kaeru sanyushi, "Three Fearless Frogs", 1933; Running time 00:07:07; 125 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0002, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0002.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; Japanese cel animation created by Noburo Ofuji (see https://animation.filmarchives.jp/en/works/view/41030)
  - untitled, circa 1937; Running time 00:10:39; 130 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0003, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0003.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; Second Sino-Japanese War, Japanese Army parade in Shanghai, aftermath of bombing, boats in harbor.
  - untitled, circa 1937; Running time 00:04:57; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0007, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0007.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; European/American couple playing with dog in yard.
  - untitled, circa 1938; Running time 00:09:23; 125 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0001, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0001.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; Americans/Europeans barbecue-ing, drinking; American/European couple with dog (related footage on RL11795-F8-0007); twin dancers/performers; men in swimsuits drinking and smoking; dog and monkey.
  - untitled, circa 1938; Running time 00:14:39; 175 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0004, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0004.mp4)
    8mm, bw, col, sil.; Beijing; Temple of Heaven; Miaoying Temple; Summer Palace; Forbidden City; Summer Palace (color); Jade Peak Pagoda (color); Tianning Temple Pagoda (color)
  - untitled, circa 1938; Running time 00:04:28; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0005, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0005.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; possibly Tianjin, tobacco market, men working, tobacco packing.
  - untitled, 1939; Running time 00:04:42; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0006, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0006.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; Tianjin flood.
  - untitled, circa 1938; Running time 00:04:28; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0008, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0008.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; possibly Shanghai; bombed factory buildings; workers removing rubble, men throwing baseball.
  - Kodak Cinegraph: Hawaii III, circa 1938; Running time 00:04:11; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0010, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0010.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; Kodak promotional
  - untitled, circa 1939; Running time 00:04:28; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0011, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0011.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; Stilt walkers gathering and parading. American couples, including Isaac Jones Young, III.
  - untitled, circa 1939; Running time 00:04:37; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0012, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0012.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; probably Shanghai; Americans on beach, including Isaac Jones Young, III.
  - untitled, circa 1939; Running time 00:04:09; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0014, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0014.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; Birthday party at Young house, 230 E. Young Avenue, Henderson NC
  - untitled, circa 1940; Running time 00:04:26; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0013, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0013.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; Shangai harbor scenes, Whangpoo Wharf; traveling through mountains; Guanlao Village(觀嶗村), near Qingdao City, Shandong Province.
  - untitled, circa 1940; Running time 00:04:28; 50 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL11795-F8-0009, Digital-materials RL11795-SET-0001; RL11795-F8-0009.mp4)
    8mm, bw, sil.; Americans, including Isaac Jones Young, III; beach scenes, Chinese couple with child